<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Flux combiné Armand Ley et Nicolas Juillet</title>
<link>https://arxiv.org</link>
<description>Publications arXiv récentes des auteurs Armand Ley et Nicolas Juillet.</description>
<docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
<generator>python-feedgen</generator>
<language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 14:46:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
<item>
<title>On A Mixture Of Brenier and Strassen Theorems</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/1808.02681v2</link>
<description>We give a characterization of optimal transport plans for a variant of the usual quadratic transport cost introduced in [33]. Optimal plans are composition of a deterministic transport given by the gradient of a continuously differentiable convex function followed by a martingale coupling. We also establish some connections with Caffarelli's contraction theorem [14].</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/1808.02681v2</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 09:14:03 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>On a solution to the Monge transport problem on the real line arising from the strictly concave case</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00681v1</link>
<description>It is well-known that the optimal transport problem on the real line for the classical distance cost may not have a unique solution. In this paper we recover uniqueness by considering the transport problems where the costs are a power smaller than one of the distance, and letting this parameter tend to one. A complete construction of this solution that we call excursion coupling is given. This is reminiscent to the one in the convex case. It is also characterized as the solution of secondary transport problems. Moreover, a combinatoric/geometric characterization of the routes used for this transport plan is provided.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00681v1</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 12:09:08 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Coupling Proof of Convex Ordering for Compound Distributions</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.07218v1</link>
<description>In this paper, we give an alternative proof of the fact that, when compounding a nonnegative probability distribution, convex ordering between the distributions of the number of summands implies convex ordering between the resulting compound distributions. Although this is a classical textbook result in risk theory, our proof exhibits a concrete coupling between the compound distributions being compared, using the representation of one-period discrete martingale laws as a mixture of the corresponding extremal measures.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.07218v1</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 08:42:29 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>SubRiemanniann structures do not satisify Riemannian Brunn--Minkowski inequalities</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.01170v1</link>
<description>We prove that no Brunn--Minkowski inequality from the Riemannian theories of curvature-dimension and optimal transportation can by satisfied by a strictly subRiemannian structure. Our proof relies on the same method as for the Heisenberg group together with new investigations by Agrachev, Barillari and Rizzi on ample normal geodesics of subRieman-nian structures and the geodesic dimension attached to them.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.01170v1</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 08:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Shadow martingales -- a stochastic mass transport approach to the peacock problem</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.10478v3</link>
<description>Given a family of real probability measures $(\mu_t)_{t\geq 0}$ increasing in convex order (a peacock) we describe a systematic method to create a martingale exactly fitting the marginals at any time. The key object for our approach is the obstructed shadow of a measure in a peacock, a generalization of the (obstructed) shadow introduced in \cite{BeJu16,NuStTa17}. As input data we take an increasing family of measures $(\nu^\alpha)_{\alpha \in [0,1]}$ with $\nu^\alpha(\mathbb{R})=\alpha$ that are submeasures of $\mu _0$, called a parametrization of $\mu_0$. Then, for any $\alpha$ we define an evolution $(\eta^\alpha_t)_{t\geq 0}$ of the measure $\nu^\alpha=\eta^\alpha_0$ across our peacock by setting $\eta^\alpha_t$ equal to the obstructed shadow of $\nu^\alpha$ in $(\mu _s)_{s \in [0,t]}$. We identify conditions on the parametrization $(\nu^\alpha)_{\alpha\in [0,1]}$ such that this construction leads to a unique martingale measure $\pi$, the shadow martingale, without any assumptions on the peacock. In the case of the left-curtain parametrization $(\nu_{\text{lc}}^\alpha)_{\alpha \in [0,1]}$ we identify the shadow martingale as the unique solution to a continuous-time version of the martingale optimal transport problem. Furthermore, our method enriches the knowledge on the Predictable Representation Property (PRP) since any shadow martingale comes with a canonical Choquet representation in extremal Markov martingales.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.10478v3</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 12:48:15 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Instability of Martingale optimal transport in dimension d $\ge$ 2</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2101.06964v1</link>
<description>Stability of the value function and the set of minimizers w.r.t. the given data is a desirable feature of optimal transport problems. For the classical Kantorovich transport problem, stability is satisfied under mild assumptions and in general frameworks such as the one of Polish spaces. However, for the martingale transport problem several works based on different strategies established stability results for R only. We show that the restriction to dimension d = 1 is not accidental by presenting a sequence of marginal distributions on R 2 for which the martingale optimal transport problem is neither stable w.r.t. the value nor the set of minimizers. Our construction adapts to any dimension d $\ge$ 2. For d $\ge$ 2 it also provides a contradiction to the martingale Wasserstein inequality established by Jourdain and Margheriti in d = 1.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2101.06964v1</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 10:11:14 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>On absolutely continuous curves in the Wasserstein space over R and their representation by an optimal Markov process</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.02495v2</link>
<description>Let $\mu$ = ($\mu$t)t$\in$R be a 1-parameter family of probability measures on R. In [11] we introduced its ``Markov-quantile''process: a process X= (Xt)t$\in$R that resembles as much as possible the quantile process attached to $\mu$, among the Markov processesattached to $\mu$, i.e. whose family of marginal laws is $\mu$.In this article we look at the case where $\mu$ is absolutely continuous in the Wasserstein space P2(R). Then X is solution of adynamical transport problem with marginals ($\mu$t)t. It provides a Markov minimal Lagrangian probabilistic representative of $\mu$, whichis moreover unique among the processes obtained as certain types of limits: limits for the finite dimensional topology of quantileprocesses where the past is made independent of the future conditionally on the present at finitely many times, or limits of processeslinearly interpolating $\mu$.This raises new questions about ways to obtain Markov Lagrangian representatives, and to seek uniqueness properties in thisframework.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.02495v2</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 07:51:17 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Taking Music Seriously: on the Dynamics of 'Mathemusical' Research with a Focus on Hexachordal Theorems</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00507v1</link>
<description>After presenting the general framework of 'mathemusical' dynamics, we focus on one music-theoretical problem concerning a special case of homometry theory applied to music composition, namely Milton Babbitt's hexachordal theorem. We briefly discuss some historical aspects of homometric structures and their ramifications in crystallography, spectral analysis and music composition via the construction of rhythmic canons tiling the integer line. We then present the probabilistic generalization of Babbitt's result we recently introduced in a paper entitled ''New hexachordal theorems in metric spaces with probability measure'' and illustrate the new approach with original constructions and examples.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00507v1</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 11:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Analytic Stockwell Transform and its Zeros</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17076v3</link>
<description>A recent original line of research in time--frequency analysis has shifted the interest in energy maxima toward zeros. Initially motivated by the intriguing uniform spread of the zeros of the spectrogram of white noise, it has led to fruitful theoretical developments combining probability theory, complex analysis and signal processing. In this vein, the present work proposes a characterization of the zeros of the Stockwell Transform of white noise, which consists in an hybrid time--frequency multiresolution representation. First of all, an analytic version of the Stockwell Transform is designed. Then, analyticity is leveraged to establish a connection with the hyperbolic Gaussian Analytic Function, whose zero set is invariant under the isometries of the Poincar\'e disk. Finally, the theoretical spatial statistics of the zeros of the hyperbolic Gaussian Analytic Function and the empirical statistics of the zeros the Analytic Stockwell Transform of white noise are compared through intensive Monte Carlo simulations, supporting the established connection. A publicly available documented Python toolbox accompanies this work.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17076v3</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 08:06:15 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>On the Markov transformation of Gaussian processes</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10001v1</link>
<description>Given a Gaussian process $(X_t)_{t \in \mathbb{R}}$, we construct a Gaussian \emph{Markov} process with the same one-dimensional marginals using sequences of transformations of $(X_t)_{t \in \mathbb{R}}$ "made Markov" at finitely many times. We prove that there exists at least such a Markov transform of $(X_t)_{t \in \mathbb{R}}$. In the case the instantaneous decorrelation rate of $(X_t)_{t \in \mathbb{R}}$ is continuous, we prove that the Markov transform is uniquely determined and characterized through the same instantaneous decorrelation rate.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10001v1</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 09:39:50 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The soccer model, stochastic ordering and martingale transport</title>
<link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07145v1</link>
<description>Tournaments are competitions between a number of teams, the outcome of which determines the relative strength or rank of each team. In many cases, the strength of a team in the tournament is given by a score. Perhaps, the most striking mathematical result on the tournament is Moon's theorem, which provides a necessary and sufficient condition for a feasible score sequence via majorization. To give a probabilistic interpretation of Moon's result, Aldous and Kolesnik introduced the soccer model,the existence of which gives a short proof of Moon's theorem. However, the existence proof of Aldous and Kolesnik is nonconstructive, leading to the question of a ``canonical'' construction of the soccer model. The purpose of this paper is to provide explicit constructions of the soccer model with an additional stochastic ordering constraint, which can be formulated by martingale transport. Two solutions are given: one is by solving an entropy optimization problem via Sinkhorn's algorithm, and the other relies on the idea of shadow couplings. It turns out that both constructions yield the property of strong stochastic transitivity. The nontransitive situations of the soccer model are also considered.</description>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07145v1</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 10:20:08 +0000</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
